Campaign for Peace and Democracy Records TAM.462
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
Campaign for Peace and Democracy Records
1968-1975; 1981-1998 [bulk dates 1981-1998]
TAM.462
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
17.0 linear feet (17 boxes)
The Campaign for Peace and Democracy (founded in 1982 as Campaign for Peace and Democracy/East and West) is dedicated to advancing a progressive and non-militaristic U.S. foreign policy -- one that encourages democracy and social justice by promoting solidarity with activists and progressive movements throughout the world. The records contain correspondence (principal correspondent is CPD founder and longtime head Joanne Landy), minutes, reports and other internal documents, political activities files, research files, printed ephemera from CPD and other organizations, Joanne Landy's personal notebooks,research materials, government documents and documents created by various Non Governmental Organizations (NGOs). NOTE: This collection is housed offsite and advance notice is required for use.
Campaign for Peace and Democracy.
Historical/Biographical Note
The Campaign for Peace and Democracy (founded in 1982 as Campaign for Peace and Democracy/East and West) is dedicated to advancing a progressive and non-militaristic U.S. foreign policy -- one that encourages democracy and social justice by promoting solidarity with activists and progressive movements throughout the world. The Campaign opposed the Cold War by calling for "detente from below," engaging Western peace activists in the defense of the rights of democratic dissidents in the Soviet Union and Eastern Europe, and enlisted East-bloc human rights activists against U.S. policies in countries like Nicaragua and Chile. Along with the European Nuclear Disarmament Movement, the Campaign built grassroots solidarity across the Cold War divide, and refused to "choose sides" in the East-West conflict.
Scope and Content Note
The records contain correspondence (principal correspondent is CPD founder and longtime head Joanne Landy), minutes, reports and other internal documents, political activities files, research files, printed ephemera from CPD and other organizations, Joanne Landy's personal notebooks,her research materials for an application for a MacArthur Foundation writing grant for a project titled "The Role of Western Economic Policy in the Transformation of Eastern Europe and the Soviet Union," government documents and documents created by various Non Governmental Organizations (NGOs). NOTE: This collection is housed offsite and advance notice is required for use.
FOR ADDITIONAL INFORMATION, CONTACT: tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu
Campaign for Peace and Democracy.; Campaign for Peace and Democracy/East and West.; Landy, Joanne; Anti-globalization movement.; Antinuclear movement.; Correspondence.; Europe, Eastern |x Foreign relations |z Soviet Union.; Human rights |z Europe, Eastern.; Human rights.; Notebooks.; Nuclear disarmament.; Peace movements |z United States.; Research (document genres).; Soviet Union |x Foreign relations |z Europe, Eastern.; Soviet Union |x Politics and government.; United States |x Foreign relations.
- Contents: Records, c.1980-1983; Peace and Democracy News, 1984-1995 (name changed to Peace and Democracy in 1994). Note: Campaign for Peace and Democracy East and West was founded in 1982, and became Campaign for Peace and Democracy in 1990. Some material is from predecessor organizations., c.1980-1995 (Box 1)
- Contents: Records, 1984-1986 (Box 2)
- Contents: Records, 1987-1989 (Box 3)
- Contents: CPD director Joanne Landy's research materials for MacArthur Foundation writing award "The Role of Western Economic Policy in tehe Transformation of Eastern Europe and the Soviet Union" (Part 1), 1990-1991 (Box 4)
- Contents: Contents: CPD director Joanne Landy's research materials for MacArthur Foundation writing award "The Role of Western Economic Policy in tehe Transformation of Eastern Europe and the Soviet Union" (Part 2), 1990-1991 (Box 5)
- Contents: Records, 1992-1993 (Box 6)
- Contents: Records, 1994-1996 (Box 7)
- Contents: Special Topics (Polish Solidarnosc, Independent Soviet Peace Group, Czechoslovakia’s Charter 77 Group), c.1985, undated (Box 8)
- Contents: Joanne Landy's personal notebooks, miscellaneous records and printed ephemera, photographs, 1968-1975 (Box 9)
- Contents: Balance sheets and receipts, 1992-1993 (Box 10)
- Contents: Receipts, etc., 1991 (Box 11)
- Contents: Miscellaneous records and printed ephemera, 1988-1991 (Box 12)
- Contents: Chronological Correspondence Notebooks: 1, 1988-c.1991 (Box 13)
- Contents: Chronological Correspondence Notebooks: 2, 1984-1998 (Box 14)
- Contents: Chronological Correspondence Notebooks: 3, 1988-1992 (Box 15)
- Contents: Chronological Correspondence Notebooks: 4, 1986-1992 (Box 16)
- Contents: Individuals: donors and others, c.1986-1994 (Box 17)